<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A verie profitable and necessarie discourse concerning the obseruation and keeping of the Sabboth day seruing as well to confute the superstition of the Iewes, which obstinately vrge the strict keeping of the seuenth day, as also to ouerthrowe the vaine and godlesse reasons of others, that stiffely at this day maintaine, that Christians ought to keepe no set or appoynted time to worship and serue the Lord in, in his church and faithfull congregation. Written in Latine by Zacharias Vrsinus, sometimes reader of the diuinitie lecture in the Vniuersitie of Heidelberg in Germanie, and very nevvly turned into English, by Iohn Stockvvood schoolemaster of Tunbridge.</title>
            <author>Ursinus, Zacharias, 1534-1583.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839367</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839367</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3777</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3777)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1612:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A verie profitable and necessarie discourse concerning the obseruation and keeping of the Sabboth day seruing as well to confute the superstition of the Iewes, which obstinately vrge the strict keeping of the seuenth day, as also to ouerthrowe the vaine and godlesse reasons of others, that stiffely at this day maintaine, that Christians ought to keepe no set or appoynted time to worship and serue the Lord in, in his church and faithfull congregation. Written in Latine by Zacharias Vrsinus, sometimes reader of the diuinitie lecture in the Vniuersitie of Heidelberg in Germanie, and very nevvly turned into English, by Iohn Stockvvood schoolemaster of Tunbridge.</title>
                  <author>Ursinus, Zacharias, 1534-1583.</author>
                  <author>Stockwood, John, d. 1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[66] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by T. East?] for Iohn Harrison the yonger,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A [-A1] B-D E² .</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3777:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3777:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VERIE PROFITABLE AND NECESSARIE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVRSE CONCERNING THE obſeruation and keeping of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day, ſeruing as well to confute the ſuperſtition of the Iewes, which obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately vrge the ſtrict keeping of the ſeuenth day, as alſo to ouerthrowe the vaine and godleſſe reaſons of others, that ſtiffely at this day maintaine, that Chriſtians ought to keepe no ſet or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted time to worſhip and ſerue the Lord in, in his Church and faithfull Congregation.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN IN LATINE BY ZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias Vrſinus, ſometimes Reader of the Diuinitie lecture in the Vniuerſitie of Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberg in Germanie, and very nevvly tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Engliſh, by Iohn Stockvvood Schoolemaſter of Tunbridge.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Imprinted for Iohn Harriſon the yonger 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3777:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3777:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Ladie, the Ladie Pellam of Laughton in the Countie of Suſſex, Iohn Stockwood Schoolemaſter of Tunbridge, vviſheth a plentifull increaſe of all ſpirituall and heauenly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in the life to come, the perfect and ful fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ioyes euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing not ignorant (right worſhipful and vertuous Ladie) of the manifolde diſputations not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the learned, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the great varietie &amp; diuerſitie of opinions among the vulgar people and ſimple ſorte, concerning the Sabboth day, &amp; the right vſe of the ſame: ſome with the wayward and ſuperſtitious Iewes obſtinately and ſtifly maintaining the ceremonial obſeruation of the ſeuenth day,<note place="margin">Sundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sabboth daye.</note> the which they hold in no wiſe to be mutable, or to be altered and changed: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with the Atheiſts and godleſſe Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures vtterly denying, that there ought to
<pb facs="tcp:3777:3"/> be any obſeruation and keping of any day at all as wholly &amp; dedicated vnto the Lorde his ſeruice: and yet moreouer ſome others, who albeit they graunt it meete &amp; requiſite that there ſhould be ſome certain &amp; ſet day of the week ſeuered out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt for the vſe of the miniſterie &amp; Church meetings, yea and the ſame alſo to bee that daye which we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly call the Sunne-day, or Lords day, yet holding it lawfull as well on the ſame day, as any other day in the week, to exerciſe the cuſtomable &amp; vſual works, euery man of his ordinarie trade &amp; vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I haue thought with my ſelfe that I could not do better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſee: out a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die for the ſtaying of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences of the weaker number in this great varietie and doubtfulnes of aſſertions, tending to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of religion and impeachment of gods ſeruice. Meeting therfore with a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; learned Worke of one Vrſinus a Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the which are profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly &amp; pithily handled many theologicall diſcourſes and points of religion, &amp; among the reſt, this of the Sabboth, in his expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the 4. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, finding the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſit for the circumſtance of the time, I haue turned the ſame into our mother tongue, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3777:3"/> benefit of the godly &amp; chriſtianly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that they may haue in this poynt wherwith to ſatisfie both the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For in this ſmal treatiſe is debated the right vſe of the Sabboth day,<note place="margin">The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</note> what exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on the ſame are allowable &amp; what to be refrained, wherin it is kept, &amp; wherin it is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: their argument co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed, that think it not lawfull for Chriſtians to keepe the the Lords day, &amp; their reaſons alſo anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which ſo ſtoutly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend for the Iewiſh obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th day: al theſe things being proued with moſt ſtrong &amp; euident proues out of the word of God and holy ſcriptures, &amp; that in ſuch ſort, that the lyke is hardly to be met withall in ſo briefe &amp; ſhort a Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phlet or treatiſe. The neceſsitie heerof is apparant in regard of the time, wherein is ſo diuerſly diſputed concerning this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the profit likewiſe ſhall eaſily (I doubt not) be reaped of all ſuch as with ſingle harts &amp; vpright mindes ſhal dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and without parcialitie peruſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>This my ſmall labour, ſuch as it is (ſimple &amp; ſlender I confeſſe, in regard of my pains in tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlating, but much behoueful &amp; auail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, in regard of the matter, for the church &amp; people of god) I make bold to offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:3777:4"/> to the gentle acceptation of your good Ladiſhip, for manie cauſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that beſides the manie other hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye graces of faith, knowledge of the will of God, loue vnto his euerlaſting truth and holy Scriptures, care to walk in life and conuerſation accordingly: with making much of the profeſſors, and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the preachers of the ſame: it maye be a further ſpur vnto you, to the ſtirring vp &amp; increaſing of your godlye zeale for the Lord his ſeruice &amp; carefull ſanctifying of his holy Sabboth, not onely in your owne perſon, but alſo in your whole familye: ſo that it may be truly ſaid of you, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God &amp; comfort of his people, as we read of that good &amp; vertuous captaine Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſchuahh: I &amp; my houſhold wil ſerue the Lord. For albeit the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber be ſmal, &amp; the people few that haue a due regard of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſpending the Lordes daye, in hearing the word preached, in receiuing the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in praier, ſupplication, &amp; thanks-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, &amp; in priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferring with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies at home, of the word publiky prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched (the greateſt multitude both of men and women of all degrees and callinges, letting looſe the raynes, and giuing
<pb facs="tcp:3777:4"/> out the bridle vnto all kinde of vanities &amp; licentiouſneſſe) yet let this be your crowne and glorie (good madame) letting theſe go, to haue imitated and followed the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of thoſe vertuous gentlewome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonica, whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Act. 17.2 3.4.</note> for their great diligence in reuerent obſeruing the Sabboth day, &amp; in vſual frequenting &amp; reſorti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to heare the word, for the great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their ſoules. And further, in the ſame place is the example of the godlye wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Beroea co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended, who not of cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e,<note place="margin">Act. 17.10.11.12</note> but of zeale, not of conſtraint, but with all willingneſſe, not as ſad &amp; heauie, but with all readyneſſe and ioyfulneſſe, not onelie heard the word preached by Paule and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, at the publike aſſemblies and meetings of the Church, but alſo vſed dailie and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate conference in their houſes at home, in ſerching the Scriptures, whether the things were ſo or no. How comfortable is that alſo which we read in the 16. of the Acts,<note place="margin">Act. 16.12.13.14.15.</note> of the practiſe of the zealous women of Philippos, who in the coldneſſe and ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of men (as may appeare, &amp; very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bablie be gathered) cuſtomablie aſſembled to the riuer without the Citie, to heare Paule preach on the Sabboth, where by
<pb facs="tcp:3777:5"/> the opening of the heart of Lydia, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lorde by the conuerſion of one poore woman to beginne his kingdome in Macedonia, which woman is praiſed not onelie for religiouſneſſe in her ſelfe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for her whole familie, beeing godlie and chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie diſpoſed. For the text doth men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſhe was baptiſed, &amp; all her houſe: which Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (no doubt) the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would not haue adminiſtred vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnleſſe he had found in them the fruites &amp; teſtimonies of true Chriſtianitie:<note place="margin">Reade the Epiſtle of S. Iohn vnto the elect lady</note> And here at no hand may wee let paſſe the worthie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, which Iohn giueth vnto the moſt vertuous &amp; worſhipful Lady and her children, whoſe conuerſation before the world was agreeable vnto their profeſsion, according as the truth of the Lord requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that it ſhould be. Which ſingular and notable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, as it generallie concerneth al chriſtian and godly women, ſo dooth it moſt neerelie and properlie belong vnto your good Ladiſhip, &amp; all other gentle wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of your place and calling.<note place="margin">Ro. 15.4.</note> For, if what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer examples of the olde fathers in the Scriptures are written for our learning, that by reading their examples, we ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:3777:5"/> expreſſe and followe their vertues, then doubtleſſe are all women of great wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe and dignitie of this godlie Ladie to learne, that it is not ſufficient that they be religious and godlie themſelues, but that they alſo labour to haue their whole fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and houſeholds vnfainedlie to feare the Lord, which thing cannot bee performed without the diligent hearing of the word on the Lords day, &amp; other meetings of the Church, and priuate labouring in inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and dailie teaching of our charges at home, the which good exerciſe, as I can hope for at the handes of manie, ſo I can promiſe and aſſure my ſelfe, that it ſhall bee carefullie practiſed of your W. of whome I heare ſo well for zeale and loue of the truth, nothing doubting but that beeing compaſſed about with ſo greate a cloude of witneſſes,<note place="margin">He. 12.1.2</note> whoſe care hath beene ſo vehement and earneſt for the true ſpending of the Sabboth, and Chriſtian education of their famylies, with performance of other dueties of Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, all lets and ſtumbling blockes being remooued, you will dailie adde vnto that great good forwardnes, which the lord hath
<pb facs="tcp:3777:6"/> wrought in you alredie a plentiful increaſe in all vertues, beautifying and garniſhing a Chriſtian Ladie, God by his holie ſpirite working in your heart a burning deſire euerie daie more and more to imitate the commendable examples of theſe holy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones before alleadged.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, hauing receiued many bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits at the hands of that worthie Knight, ſir Iohn Pellam, your late deceaſed husband, a Gentleman ſo well deſeruing of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth and Countrie, that verie enuie her ſelfe, if neuer ſo faine ſhe woulde, ſhall yet neuer be able to burie in the dark lake of obliuion his due deſerued praiſes: I haue thought it meete and requiſite to giue out before the world ſome dutifull teſtimonie of a thankfull minde in regard of the ſame, leaſt I might worthilie be condempned of that vice which is both hated of God and deteſted of men, I meane the foule ſtaine of ingratitude, which the verie Heathen haue recorded to be the chiefe ring-leader vnto all filthineſſe,<note place="margin">Xenopho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> In his firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooke of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation of Cyrus.</note> as being alwaies accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with bluſhles ſhameleſneſſe, which may eaſily perſwade vnto al kind of wickednes.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, in regard of your owne W. omitting ſuch good graces, as are generally
<pb facs="tcp:3777:6"/> knowen by the working of God his ſpirite to be in you, to the comfort of the godlie, (becauſe that you of your modeſtie cannot abide to heare them, nor I without ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of flatterie may be thought to name them) the particular knowledge of vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued gentlenes from your good L. meant vnto me, moſt worthilie craueth ſome du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſignification of my gratefull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of ſuch moſt curteous kindneſſe, the which, becauſe my poore abilitie wyll ſuffer no other waie to expreſſe, accept (I moſt humblie beſeech you) theſe paper thanks, vntil God ſhall offer ſome fitter oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to teſtifie that vnfained thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which your ſingular courteſie moſt iuſtlie doth require, praying in the meane ſeaſon the Lord, moſt abundauntlie in this life to direct you in all your waies to his glorie, and ioy of his choſen, and in the life to come to make you partaker of thoſe vnſpeakable bleſsings, which in moſt rich mercy he hath prepared for all thoſe that in his Chriſt do trulie feare and ſerue him, to whome be all glorie both now and for euer Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tunbridge, the 20. of Oct. 1584.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your W. moſt humble Iohn Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Schoolemaſter of Tunbridge.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb facs="tcp:3777:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3777:7"/>
            <head>A RIGHT GOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and learned expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition vpon the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, concerning the Sabboth, and right vſe of the ſame.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>The fourth Commandement.</bibl>
               <q>REmember that thou keepe holie the Sabboth daie. Sixe daies ſhalt thou worke, and doe all thy worke: but the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth daie there ſhall bee a Sabboth vnto the Lord thy God. Thou ſhalt doe no worke, neither thou, nor thy ſonne, nor thy daughter, nor thy ſeruaunt, nor thy maide, nor thy cattell, nor the ſtraunger which is within thy gates. For in ſixe daies the Lord made heauen, earth, the ſea, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer are in them, and reſted the ſeauenth daie, and therefore he bleſſed the ſeauenth daie, and hallowed it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head type="sub">The expoſition.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two parts of this lawe, the commandement, &amp; the reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. And again, there are two parts of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, of the which the one is morall or euerlaſting, namelie,
<pb facs="tcp:3777:8"/> that the Sabboth be hallowed,<note place="margin">What is morall &amp; for euer in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What is ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all &amp; for a time.</note> that is to ſaie, that ſome certaine time be appointed for the miniſterie of the Church, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like worſhippe of God. The other is cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, and for a time, namelie, that this time ſhuld be the ſeuenth daie, and that in it ſhould be obſerued and kept the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Leuiticall lawe. And that this part is for a time, and the other euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, we doe vnderſtand by the end of the commaundement, and cauſes of both theſe parts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ende of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie.</note>The end of the commaundement is the publike praiſing of God in the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the conſeruation or maintenance and vſe of the miniſterie of the Church, which is an office ordained by God, to teach the Church concerning God and his will out of the word of God deliuered by the Prophets and Apoſtles, and to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſacraments according to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of God. And God would haue at all times of the world that there ſhuld be publique aſſemblies of the Church, in the which ſhould ſound true doctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God, for theſe cauſes eſpecially.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt: that in mankinde God might be praiſed and called vpon,<note place="margin">Cauſes of ordeining the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie.</note> not onely pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately,
<pb facs="tcp:3777:8"/> but alſo with the publike voyce of the Church in this life, Pſalm. 68. <hi>In the Congregations bleſſe ye the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond: that the publike and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> preaching of doctrine, the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of prayers, and thankes-giuing, and vſing of ceremonies might be an exerciſe ſtirring vp and foſtering faith and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as the which without exerciſes by reaſon of our infirmitie and weakeneſſe doth very eaſely were colde. Epheſ. 4. <hi>He hath giuen ſome Apoſtles, others Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, others Euangeliſts, others Paſtors, and Doctors vnto the worke of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, vnto the edifying of the bodie of Chriſt: vntill we all come vnto the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Sonne of GOD, vnto a perfect man, vnto the meaſure of the ſtature of Chriſt full growen, that wee be no longer children, which do wauer, and are caried about with euerie winde of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, &amp;c.</hi> The third: that one ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and ſtir vp another by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto godlines, and vnto the prayſing of God. Pſa. 22. <hi> I wil ſhew forth thy name vnto my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the middeſt of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation will I praiſe thee: yee that feare the Lord praiſe him, the whole ſeede of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob
<pb facs="tcp:3777:9"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> glorifie him, &amp;c.</hi> The fourth: that conſent and agréement in doctrine, and in the worſhip of God might be kepte in the church. Eph. 4. <hi>He hath giuen Paſtors and Doctours vnto the growing together of the Saints, vntill that we all attaine vnto the vnitie of faith.</hi> The fifth: that the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> church may be ſéene &amp; heard in mankind, and diſcerned &amp; knowen from the other multitude of men blaſphemons &amp; idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous. And God will haue the Church to be ſéene, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elect may be gathered vnto it, and the reprobate or off-caſtes become the more inexcuſable, whileſt they deſpiſe the voyce heard, and the calling of God, &amp; goe about to repreſſe and keepe backe the ſame. Rom. 10. <hi>But haue they not heard? yea the ſound of them hath gone forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the earth, and their wordes into the endes of the world.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>Thankes be vnto God, who cauſeth, that we alwaies tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in Chriſt, &amp; by vs in all places doth make manifeſt the ſauor of his knowledge. For we are the good ſauour of Chriſt vnto God, in thoſe which are ſaued, and in thoſe which doo periſh: to theſe the ſauour of death vnto death, &amp; vnto them the ſauour of life vnto life. Luc.</hi> 2. <hi> Behold he is ſet vp
<pb facs="tcp:3777:9"/> vnto the fall and riſing againe of many in Iſrael, and for a ſigne that ſhall be ſpoken againſt, that the thoughts may be layde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen out of manie hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe cauſes appertaine not vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one certein time, but vnto al times of the Church and of the world. Therefore God wil alwaies haue the miniſterie of his Church preſerued, and the vſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe therof frequented, practiſed, &amp; haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:<note place="margin">The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parte of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall &amp; euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> and therefore the kinde of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, or the morall part therof, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the world euen vnto the end, doth binde al men, namely that ſome Sabboth be kept, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome time be appointed for ſermons, &amp; publike prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and miniſtring of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacraments. But contrariwiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuenth day was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God vnto the miniſterie euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, to ſignifie,<note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the ſeauenth daye.</note> that men after the example of God ought to reſt from their works, that is to ſay, from their daily labours belonging vnto this life, but eſpecially from ſinne, &amp; giue them ſelues wholly vnto the meditation and thinking vpon, and vnto the praiſing and ſetting forth of the workes of God.</p>
            <p>And afterwards this commandement
<pb facs="tcp:3777:10"/> was rehearſed again in the lawe of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church</note> and the ceremonie of reſting the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth daie was withall made a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is to ſaie, a token of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherby God did ſignifie, that he was the ſanctifier of the Church, that is, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue her her ſinnes, to receiue her into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, to endue and gouerne her by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt, to the beginning of a new and euerlaſting life in this life, and afterward to be perfected and finiſhed for and by the promiſed Meſſias. <hi>Exo.</hi> 31. <hi>Ye ſhal keep my Sabboths: becauſe it is a ſigne betweene me and you in your generations, that yee may know that I am the Lord, which doo ſanctifie you. Ezech.</hi> 20. <hi>And I haue giuen vnto them my Sabboths, that they ſhould be for a ſigne betweene me and them, that they ſhuld know that I am the Lord which doe ſanctifie them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of kee ing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeauenth daie, ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> avvaie by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Foraſmuch then as the Sabboth of the ſeauenth daie was a figure putting the people in minde both of their duetie, or of godlyneſſe towards God, and of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of God performed towardes his people by Chriſt: it was with other ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies taken awaie by the comming of Chriſt, by whome that was fulfilled the
<pb facs="tcp:3777:10"/> which thoſe ceremonies did ſignifie, which thing alſo <hi>Paule</hi> doeth witneſſe <hi>Colloſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Let no man therefore condempne you for meate, or drinke, or in regard of an holie daie, or new moone, or Sabboths, the which are a ſhadowe of things to come, but the bodie is of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Iewes obiect:<note place="margin">Obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th day. Obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th daie is the cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moniall part. Anſvvere.</note> foraſmuch as we eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues confeſſe, that the law of the ten commaundements is perpetuall or euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting: and that the precept touching the Sabboth is part of the ten Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, therefore it is not to be aboliſhed or taken awaie.</p>
            <p>We anſwere, that the Decalogue or ten commaundements is perpetuall or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting, ſo far as it is morall: and that the additions or circumſtances of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall commaundements for ſignification ſake, were to be kept no longer then vntil the comming of the Meſſias.</p>
            <p>Secondlie they replie, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
               </label> that it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten concerning the Sabboth. <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. <hi>It is an euerlaſting couenant: it is an euerlaſting ſigne betweene me &amp; the ſonnes of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We anſwere, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſvvere. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both is euerlaſt.</note> firſt that the ceremonial Sabboth is perpetuall vnto the comming of Chriſt, which was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of ceremonies.
<pb facs="tcp:3777:11"/> 
               <hi>Ierem.</hi> 31. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. Secondly, that the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both is euerlaſting, concerning the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, which is a ceaſing from ſinne, and a reſt in the Lord. For ſo all the figures of the olde lawe are euerlaſting, yea, &amp; the kingdome of <hi>Dauid</hi> it ſelfe, the which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding was to be deſtroied before the comming of the Meſſias. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. <hi>The Scepter ſhal not be taken awaie from Iuda vntill Silo come.</hi> And 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. <hi>Thy throne ſhall be ſure for euer. Ezech.</hi> 37. <hi>My ſeruant Dauid ſhall be a Prince vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for euer.</hi> In the ſame place, <hi>And the Gentiles ſhall know, that I the Lord doe ſanctifie Iſrael, foraſmuch as my ſanctuarie ſhal be among them for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō. </seg>3</label> Thirdlie they ſaie: albeit it ſhould bée graunted, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ceremonies of Moſes are mutable or ſuch as may be chaunged, yet the lawes giuen before Moſes are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaungeable, amongeſt the which is alſo the kéeping of the ſeauenth daie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſvvere. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies euen before Moſes vvere fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures.</note>We denie the Maior, as touching cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: for ceremonies ordeined by God before Moſes, becauſe they were figures of benefites to be receiued in the Meſſias to come, are taken away by his comming, as circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion giuen vnto <hi>Abraham:</hi> as
<pb facs="tcp:3777:11"/> alſo the ſacrifices commaunded vnto our firſt parents.</p>
            <p>Fourthlie they replie: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō. </seg>4</label>
               <note place="margin">The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both after the fall is made a figure.</note> That the lawes giuen by God before the fall, are not fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of benefits to be receiued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, and that they do bind all mankinde at all times: for then as at that time the promiſe concerning the Meſſias was not yet giuen, and there was one &amp; the ſame condition &amp; eſtate of all mankind, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which was comprehended in our firſt parents: but the Sabboth of the ſeuenth day was ordained of God, after the creation of the world was finiſhed, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fall of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: therefore it is vniuerſall and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſvvere. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>We anſwere by diſtinguiſhing of the Maior: the which is true concerning mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall lawes, the natural knowledges wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were imprinted in the mind of man in the creation, but is not true as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ceremonie or kéeping of the ſeuenth day, as which after the fall in the lawe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was made a figure of the benefites to be receiued in the Meſſias, and therefore lyke as other ceremonies, either then, or before ordeined, was made ſubiect vnto chaunge by the comming of the Meſſias.
<pb facs="tcp:3777:12"/> For God woulde not haue ſhadowes of things to come to remain, the things the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues being exhibited and giuen alredie. Albeit therefore that we graunt, that the exerciſes of the worſhippe of God on the ſeauenth day were to be obſerued &amp; kept by the commandement of God, as wel as if men had not ſinned (like as the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of abſteining from the trée of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and euill) as after they had ſinned: yet after that God placed this ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie among the ſhadowes of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias to come, by this ſelfe ſame new lawe giuen by Moſes, he made the ſame chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable together with the other Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect∣on. </seg>5</label>
               <note place="margin">The ende of this precept may bee obtained anie daye.</note>If fifthly it be obiected: The cauſe of a law being perpetuall, maketh the lawe alſo to be perpetuall: but the cauſe of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the ſeuenth daye, namely the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce and ſetting forth of the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and the meditating and thinking vpon the workes of God is perpetuall: Therfore the law of the ſeuenth day, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after that Chriſt is come, is vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſvvere. </seg>
               </label> Héere alſo we diſtinguiſh the Maior, namely that the law is vnchangeable in
<pb facs="tcp:3777:12"/> regard of the cauſe or end vnchangeable, if that cauſe or ende doo neceſſarilye and perpetually require this law as an effect or meanes: but not ſo, if at other times, and by other means we may better come vnto that end, or if the law-maker by an other law may as well attaine vnto the ſame end. Foraſmuch then, as there may be a meditation and ſetting forth of the workes of God, as well vppon an other day, as vpon the ſeuenth day, as at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning for a cauſe applied vnto the firſt times, God ordeined the ſeuenth daye for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſterie, ſo afterward for a cauſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto the times of the Meſſias being come, he abrogated or toke away the ſame lawe, and lefte it at libertie vnto the Church to chooſe other dayes: Which Church for a probable and reaſonable cauſe, choſe the firſt day, on the which the riſing againe of Chriſt fell, by the which a ſpiritual &amp; euerlaſting Sabboth is begun in vs.<note place="margin">The Lord his daye ordeined in the time of the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</note> And that this change &amp; alteration was made by the Church in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> times of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, it appeareth out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 20. chapter of the Acts: <hi>The firſt day of the weeke, the Diſciples being gathered together to break bread, Paule preached. Apoc.</hi> 1. <hi>I was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:3777:13"/> in the ſpirite vpon the Lords day.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Againſt the reaſon of thoſe which diſpute againſt the obſeruation or keeping of the firſt day of the weeke, commonlye called the Sunday.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō. </seg>
                  </label> But againſt this kéeping alſo of the firſt day among the chriſtians ſome haue diſputed, ſaying that Paule Coloſ. 2. Gal. 4. Rom. 14. forbiddeth in the Church of Chriſt difference of dayes, and therefore that the kéeping of the firſt day or Sunne day is no leſſe to be diſallowed then the obſeruing of the ſeuenth day.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſvvere. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <note place="margin">Our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the Lord his daie diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from the Ievv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both.</note>Vnto theſe we muſt anſwere by the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the Iewiſh and Chriſtian ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation. The kéeping of the Lorde his day doth differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iewiſh Sabboth: firſt, for that the Sabboth of the ſeuenth day, as a ceremonial part of the worſhip of God, might not be omitted of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes or chaunged, becauſe of the expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God: but the Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 In reſpect of vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and neceſsitie.</note> whether it appoint the firſt day or anie other day for the miniſterie, doth it without the breach of her libertie to do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, if there be iuſt cauſe, that is to
<pb facs="tcp:3777:13"/> ſay, without the opinion of neceſſitie or worſhip. Secondly,<note place="margin">2 In reſpect of the figure.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Sabboth was a figure or ſhadow of things in the new te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament to be fulfilled by Chriſt: but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new teſtament y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignification hath cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; regard is onely had of order &amp; come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, without the which there can be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no miniſterie of the Church at all, or els not ordered wel, and as it ought to be.</p>
               <p>As concerning the words of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,<note place="margin">Fiue ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fications of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vvord Sabboth.</note> this name Sabboth is firſt of all peculiarly attributed vnto the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth daye, becauſe of God his reſting fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the creation of the world, &amp; becauſe of the reſt of the people of God that day to bee obſerued. Secondly, it ſignifieth alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feaſts, in which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people were to reſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as well as on the 7. day, as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt day of Eaſter, <hi>Leui.</hi> 23. <hi>The next day after the Sabboth the Prieſt ſhall offer a Gomer.</hi> For the feaſt of trumpets, in the ſame place. <hi>In the ſeauenth moneth, on the firſt daie of the ſame, you ſhal haue a Sabboth, a token of ſounding with trumpets, an holy conuocation or aſſembly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo for the feaſt of Tabernacles: The fiftéenth day of the fifth moneth ye ſhall kéepe a feaſt vnto the Lorde, ſeuen dayes:
<pb facs="tcp:3777:14"/> on the firſt daie ſhall be a Sabboth, and on the eight daie alſo ſhall be a Sabboth. In this ſenſe and ſignification the name Sabboth agréeth alſo vnto the daies, in which in the new Teſtament the Church doth exerciſe the publike worſhip of God.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdlie, by a figure called <hi>Synechdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che,</hi> they alſo call a weeke of daies a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, as <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23. <hi>From the daie in which ye offer a Gomer of lifting vp, there ſhall be ſeuen full weekes, Math. 28.</hi> On the laſt Sabboth, when as it dawned into the firſt daie of the Sabboths, that is to ſaie, of the wéeke. <hi>Marke.</hi> 16. <hi>Verie earlie the firſt daie of the Sabboths,</hi> that is, of the wéeke, <hi>they came vnto the Sepulchre.</hi> And from hence, by a figure called <hi>Cathacreſis,</hi> it is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for a wéeke of yeares. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 25. <hi>Thou ſhalt number vnto thee ſeauen Sabboths of yeares,</hi> that is to ſaie, <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uen times ſeuen yeares, the which daies of ſeuen Sabbothes of yeares will make</hi> 49 <hi>yeares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthlie, it is taken for euerie ſeuenth yeare, in which the people of the Iewes was commaunded to leaue off the tilling of their ground. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 25. <hi> When as yee ſhall enter into the land, the which I giue vnto you, then the land ſhall keepe a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both
<pb facs="tcp:3777:14"/> vnto the Lord. Sixe yeares thou ſhalt ſowe thy ground, &amp;c. but in the ſeauenth yeare there ſhall be a Sabboth of reſt vnto the land, a Sabboth vnto the Lorde: thou ſhalt not ſowe thy field, nor cut thy vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi> And Chap. 26. <hi>Then the land ſhall finiſh her Sabbothes, all the daies in which ſhe hath bene deſolate and waſt, becauſe ſhe reſted not in your Sabboths, whileſt ye dwelled in her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthlie, by this word Sabboth is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ſpirituall reſt, that is to ſay,<note place="margin">A Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both.</note> cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from ſinne, or the leauing off of our owne workes, and the execution or dooing of the workes of God, that is, of ſuch as are by him commaunded vnto vs, and doo appertaine vnto his worſhip and glorie. This ſpirituall Sabboth is begun in this life in them that are conuerted, and is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the life euerlaſting: and is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Sabboth or reſt, both becauſe this is indeede a true reſt from labours and miſeries, and our hallowing and dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto the worſhippe of God, and alſo becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in times paſt it was ſignified by the ceremonial Sabboth. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. <hi> There is therfore lefte ſome reſt vnto the people of GOD. For hee that is entered into
<pb facs="tcp:3777:15"/> his reſt, reſted alſo himſelf from his works, as God reſted from his. Let vs ſtudie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to enter into that reſt, &amp;c. Ieſ.</hi> 66. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſſe, that from moneth to moneth, and from Sabboth vnto Sabboth all fleſh ſhall come, &amp; worſhip before me, ſayth the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">With this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement agreeth the 1.2. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fication of the vvorde Sabboth.</note>Out of theſe ſignifications of the word, the firſt and the ſecond haue place in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the wordes, &amp; the fifth by an allegorie: This alſo doth the manner of the figures ſhew, in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deining of the which God will alwayes haue their ſignification to bée vnderſtoode and obſerued. And <hi>Eſayas,</hi> chapter 28. <hi>If thou tourne awaie thy foote from the Sabboth, that thou doe not thine owne will on mine holie daie, and call the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both thy delight, that it be holie, honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto the Lord, and ſhalt honour it, that thou doo not thine owne wayes, that thine own will be not found and that thou finde not a word.</hi> And therefore with a vehemencie he ſaith, as of a thing moſt ſtraightlie commaunded: <hi>Remember that thou keepe holie the Sabboth daie,</hi> that is, that with greate care and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thou hallowe it. And Exod. 31. Hée
<pb facs="tcp:3777:15"/> commaundeth him to be put to death, which ſhall breake the Sabboth. Alſo E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech 20. and 22. When as he complaineth of the corruption of the whole worſhippe of God: he ſayth that the Sabboth is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: of which ſtraightneſſe in requiring of the kéeping of the Sabboth, there are euidentlie apparant two cauſes eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: The one, for that the neglecting of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> miniſterie of the Church doeth verie eaſilie corrupt and blot out the doctrine and worſhippe of GOD: The other, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for that by the ſtraight requiring of the figuratiue Sabboth, GOD woulde declare the greatneſſe and neceſſitie of the thing ſignified, to wit, of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sabboth. The ſame may bée vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode by the ende of the ceremoniall and morall commandement touching the Sabboth. For GOD will haue the externall or outwarde Sabboth to ſerue vnto the beginning and finiſhing in vs of the ſpirituall Sabboth. Hée will not therefore haue that obſerued and kepte without this. Finallie, héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this ſame is manifeſt, in that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth the Sabboth to bée hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that is, not to bée ſpent in laſie
<pb facs="tcp:3777:16"/> idlenes, but to haue ſinne to be auoyded, and holy workes to be done therein.<note place="margin">VVhat it is to keep holy the Sabboth.</note> For God is ſayd to halow the Sabboth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he appoynteth it vnto the worſhip of God: men alſo are commanded to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, that is to ſay, to apply it vnto that ende wherevnto it is ordeined by God, or to doo thoſe things the which God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded in the ſame to be done. Héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto apperteyneth that he ſaith that it is a Sabboth vnto the Lord, that is, dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto his worſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sixe daies of vvorke</note>And therefore appointing ſixe dayes for other labours, and the ſeuenth vnto the worſhip of God, his meaning is not that the other dayes the worſhip of God, and thinking vppon the workes of God ſhould be omitted or lefte off. For it is ſaid Deut. 6. and 11. <hi>Thou ſhalt rehearſe them vnto thy ſonnes, and ſhalt ſpeake of them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou ſhalt ſit in thine houſe, and when as thou ſhalt walke by the way, and when as thou ſhalt lye in thy bed, and when thou ſhalt ariſe.</hi> And Pſalme. 1. <hi>His pleaſure is in the lawe of the Lord,<note place="margin">Tvvo things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. 1</note> and hee meditateth and ſtudieth thereon daye and night.</hi> But he requireth theſe two things, the firſt, that on the Sabboth daye, not
<pb facs="tcp:3777:16"/> onelie the priuate, as at other times,<note place="margin">2 On the Sabboth the works of our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie calling ought to ceaſe.</note> but alſo the publike worſhip of God be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in the Church: the other, that at that time other labours, which on other daies euerie man doth exerciſe according vnto his vocation &amp; calling, ſhould giue place as well vnto the priuate, as publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</p>
               <p>Yet Iewiſh ſuperſtition is to bée ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken héede off,<note place="margin">It is lavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful on the Sabboth to doo vvorks the vvhich do not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erciſe of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie.</note> the which alſo Chriſt in the Goſpell doth often confute, namelie, that it was vnlawfull on the Sabboth daye to doe anie workes appertaining vnto the neceſſitie of their owne lyfe, or the life of others, for it appeareth by the end of the commaundement, that onelie ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile workes, or ſuch as hinder the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the miniſterie, are forbidden by God, and not ſuch as doe not hinder the publike worſhippe of God, or elſe doe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nouriſh and ſet forth the ſame. So <hi>Math.</hi> 12. Chriſt defendeth his Diſciples plucking the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res of corne on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both daie to driue awaie hunger, healeth him that had a withered hand. <hi>Luke.</hi> 13. Healeth a woman that had béene ſicke 18. yeares. And Chapter 14. Healeth one ſicke of the dropſie. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. Healeth
<pb facs="tcp:3777:17"/> one that had an infirmitie 38. yeares, and biddeth him carrie awaie his bed. And Mathew. 12. Luke. 14. ſayth, That with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie ſinne on the Sabboth daie cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell or beaſtes falling into a ditch, are thence drawen out, and Luke 13. That cattell are looſed and driuen to water. And <hi>Iudas Machabeus</hi> fought on the Sabboth, that there might be ſome to kéepe the Sabboth. 2. <hi>Machab.</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>And of this and ſuch like acts two reaſons are giuen. 1. <hi>Machab.</hi> 2. <hi>If we ſo do, as our brethren haue done, that wee fight not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Gentiles for our life &amp; religion, they will now on a ſodaine driue vs out of the land. Therefore they appointed within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues within with theſe words: what me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer ſhall by battaile ſet vpon vs on the Sabboth daie, we wil fight with them, leaſt we all die, as our brethren are dead. For the defence of their life and religion, they ſaie well, that they may ſight euen on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both daie.</hi> With the ſame reaſons Chriſt defendeth himſelfe and his Diſciples. <hi>Math.</hi> 12. rehearſing a ſaying out of the 6. Chapter of <hi>Oſeas: But if yee had knowen, what this is, I will haue mercie
<pb facs="tcp:3777:17"/> and not ſacrifice, yee woulde not haue condemned the innocents and guiltleſſe.</hi> And <hi>Marke.</hi> 2. <hi>The Sabboth was made for man, and not man for the Sabboth,</hi> that is, the ceremoniall workes ought to giue place vnto the morall, that rather the ceremonies bée omitted, then the workes of loue, the which either our owne neceſſitie, or of our neighbour doth require. And Math. 12. <hi>Haue yee not read in the lawe, that on the Sabboth the Prieſtes in the Temple prophane the Sabboth, and are without faulte? And I ſaie vnto you, that one greater then the Temple is heere.</hi> Alſo <hi>Iohn.</hi> 7. <hi>On the Sabboth yee circumciſe a man. If a man receiue circumciſion on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, and yet the lawe of Moſes is not broken, are yee offended with mee, that I haue cured an whole man on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both?</hi> In which wordes hee teacheth that ſuch workes, as hinder not the exerciſe of the Sabboth, but rather ſet foorth and confirme the ſame, ſuch as are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he workes pertaining vnto the worſhip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God, or vnto holie ceremonies, or vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he loue of our neighbour, in ſuch ſorte,
<pb facs="tcp:3777:18"/> that neceſſitie will not ſuffer them to bée put off vntill another time, doe not break the Sabboth, but are eſpeciallie required to the right obſeruation and kéeping of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Families.</note>He will haue our families alſo and our children to ceaſe from labours, for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> two cauſes: firſt and principallie, that theſe alſo by their parents and maſters maye bee brought vp and inſtructed in the worſhip of God, and to be admitted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> accuſtomed vnto the exerciſe of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the church: for he wil haue theſe alſo reckoned among the members of his Church, and doth exhort them by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his reſt vnto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Sabboth Secondlie, becauſe he wil haue loue and bountifulneſſe towardes our neighbours, to bée exerciſed and ſeene in his Church, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h in our whole life, and alſo eſpeciallie on the Sabboth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee reciteth this cauſe alſo of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſt, or ſabboth, albeit it be acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall and a ſecond came, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſt from labours might be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aunted vnto ſeruant and our familie, &amp; by calling to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce the bondage in Aeg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pt, hée exho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth the Iew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to vſe c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rteſie toward
<pb facs="tcp:3777:18"/> their ſeruants, the which they in bondage wiſhed to be ſhewed vnto themſelues. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. <hi>That thy man-ſeruaunt and thy maide-ſeruant may reſt as well as thou: &amp; remember that thou waſt a ſeruaunt in the land of Aegypt, and that the Lord thy God brought thee thence by a ſtrong ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and a ſtretched out arme. Therefore the Lord thy God hath commaunded thee to keepe the Sabboth daie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hée commaundeth alſo ſtraungers to leaue off their labours,<note place="margin">Strangers.</note> ſuch as were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted vnto true religion, like as Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites and of the houſeholde of the Church: and ſuch as were ſtill Infidels he alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth to ceaſe from labour, not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of themſelues, but in reſpect of the Iſraelites, and that for two cauſes: firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> leaſt by their example they ſhould giue offence vnto the Church: ſecondlie, leaſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> their libertie might bee an occaſion vnto the Iewes by them to doe workes on the Sabboth, which by themſelues it was not lawfull for them to doe, and ſo iniurie ſhould bée done vnto the lawe of GOD,<note place="margin">Note this vvell.</note> the which forbiddeth, not onelie by our ſelues, but alſo by others to do ſuch works and buſineſſe on the Sabboth as call
<pb facs="tcp:3777:19"/> men awaie from the worſhippe of God, and ſtudying vpon the workes and will of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Three queſtions</note>And héere out appeareth an anſwere vnto thrée queſtions or obiections.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Whether other nations alſo were bound vnto the Iewiſh ceremonies, if they dwelled amongſt the Iewes?</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Whether ſtraungers from the Church, may or ought to bee compelled vnto reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And, whether the Sacraments, amongſt the which alſo the Sabboth was, ought to be common vnto the Infidels with the Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſvvere vnto the firſt and ſecond queſtion.</note>For as concerning binding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, the ſtraungers which dwelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iewes were not conſtrayned either vnto al ceremonies, or religion, but vnto the outward diſcipline, the which was neceſſarie for the auoiding of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Church, in which they liued: for the magiſtrate ought to be the kéeper of diſcipline, according vnto both tables of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Decalogue, or ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt his ſubiects, both to forbid manifeſt idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and blaſphemies: and alſo concerning
<pb facs="tcp:3777:19"/> forrainers &amp; ſtrangers, ſo far as he may, to take héed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> open offences be not giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his ſubiectes. Furthermore, as touching binding ther was an eſpecial conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Sabboth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which was not at length by Moſes, but euen from the beginning of the world, commaunded vnto all men by God, and therfore bound all men vnto the comming of the Meſſias, albeit that this commandement was ſo farre growen out of vſe among them, that it was reckoned among the chiefe reproches, wherewithall they mocked and taunted the Iewes.<note place="margin">3 Vnto the third. The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both was no Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidells.</note> But this ceremonie was no Sacrament vnto the Infidels, becauſe that neither this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe appertained vnto them, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord would be the ſanctifier of them, neither were they conſtrained to ceaſe from their ordinarie workes for the teſtifying or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing of this promiſe, but onelie to auoid offence and occaſion of ſinning, which by them might bee giuen vnto the people of GOD: for ſo <hi>Nehem.</hi> 10. The people promiſe by oath, that on the Sabboth and holie daies, they woulde not receiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thing of the people of the lande, the which brought merchaundiſe or victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to ſell on the Sabboth daie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3777:20"/>
               <p>And Chap. 13. <hi>Nehemias</hi> by ſhutting the gates and garriſon of ſouldiours, kéepeth the <hi>Tyrians</hi> dwelling at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and bringing in wares to be ſolde on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, from comming that day into the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, leaſt occaſion might be giuen vnto the Iewes to breake the Sabboth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cattell.</note>Theſe things are better vnderſtood by this, that the Cattell alſo are commanded to reſt, whoſe reſt had no ſignification ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the worſhip of God or any ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but was commanded in regarde of the men, firſt that occaſion of working might be cut off from them, the labour or vſe of their cattell being forbidden: and ſecondly, that ſparing their brute beaſts, they might learn, how great a regard god would haue of gentleneſſe and equitie to be vſed towards men: the which cauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Paule alledgeth of the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of not muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne. 1. Cor. 9 <hi>Hath the Lord a care of Oxen? or doth he not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſay this for vs? For, for vs is this written, that he which ploweth ought to plow in hope: and he that treadeth out the corne in hope, ought to be partaker of his hope, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3777:20"/>
               <p>The reaſon which is added,<note place="margin">The reſon of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the reſt of God.</note> taken from God his reſting, apperteineth vnto the circumſtance or ceremoniall precept con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſeuenth day: <hi>God reſted on that day:</hi> that is to ſay, he ceaſed to make new parts of the world, as which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie perfected and finiſhed, and ſuch as God would haue it for to be. This daye therefore he dedicated or appoynted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worſhip of God: firſt,<note place="margin">VVhy the ſeauenth day vvas appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</note> that by the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> example of his reſt, as by a moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and ſtrong argument, he might exhort men vnto the following of him, in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing off of the ordinarie works of the 6. dayes, as God on the ſeuenth daye reſted from the workes of the ſixe dayes, that is from the creating of newe partes of the world.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that this reſt of the ſeuenth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> day might be a monument and token of the perfecting and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iſhing of the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by God, and of the continuing on that day of the perpetual preſeruation and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning of his workes, vnto his glorie &amp; benefit of his elect and choſen, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might be a ſpur vnto the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſetting forth of theſe works and benefites towardes mankinde, for whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:3777:21"/> ſake all other things are made and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by God, that out of the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, made and formed after his owne image, he might gather and preſerue a Church vnto himſelfe, the which in this life and for euer might praiſe him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tvvo-fold</note>Now the imitation and following of his reſt, vnto the which by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample he doth exhort vs, is of two ſorts: ceremoniall, and ſignifying: and morall or ſpirituall, or ſignified. For the workes, the which are called the workes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of men, are of two ſorts: for ſome are by God commanded vnto euerie particular perſon, but yet hindering the publike worſhip of God, if they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion or ceaſing, namelye the workes of euerie man his proper vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and calling, the miniſterie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, and ſuch things as appertaine vnto the exerciſe and preſeruation of the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Some are forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinnes, the which are in ſuch ſort y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per workes of the diuell and of men, that in this reſpect that they are ſinnes, they can in no wiſe be referred vnto God.</p>
               <p>Both theſe kindes of workes of men are forbidden, but in a three-fold difference of
<pb facs="tcp:3777:21"/> forbidding.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, workes are forbidden in a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> certaine reſpect,<note place="margin">Three dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces in vvorkes forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> namely ſo farre foorth as they hinder the miniſterie of the church, or giue offence: but ſinnes are forbidden ſimply.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, for that workes are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> forbidden on the Sabboth daye: but ſinnes are commanded to be lefte at all times.</p>
               <p>The thirde, for that the ceaſing from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> workes, is a figure, but the ceaſing from ſinnes is the thing ſignified by the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, and therefore ordeined by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynting of this figure, according vnto the expoſition of the figure ſet down Heb. 4. <hi>He that is entered into his reſt, reſted alſo himſelfe from his workes, as God did from his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſumme therefore of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is,<note place="margin">The ſum of the 4. comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> that it eſtabliſheth the publike worſhip of god, or miniſtery of the church, and the exerciſe and honour of the ſame. For this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> halowing, or holy of vſe the Sabboth, that is to ſaye, of the time appoynted vnto the miniſterie, when as on that day, holy workes, the which God
<pb facs="tcp:3777:22"/> hath commanded at that time to be done, are exerciſed.<note place="margin">The vvorks of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both.</note> Now the partes of this ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, or the workes of the Sabboth, the which on the Sabboth ought to bee done partly by the Miniſters and partly by the Church, are theſe eſpecially.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 To teach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church.</note>Truly to teach the Church concerning God, and his will. For in this place is ſpoken of the dutie of the Miniſters of the Church, vnto whom it appertaineth not onely in the publike aſſemblyes of the Church, faithfully to deliuer &amp; teach true doctrine, but as neceſſitie &amp; occaſion ſhall be offered, to inſtruct and admoniſh euen particular perſons, and to employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto the amendment and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all them that are committed to their charge.<note place="margin">Proues for publike doctrine.</note> Concerning doctrine in the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Church there is ſpoken Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 12. <hi>The firſt and ſeuenth day of Eaſter, there ſhall be vnto you an holy conuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or aſſembling together.</hi> Leuit. 10. <hi>That ye teach the children of Iſrael all the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes which the Lord hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the hand of Moſes.</hi> Act. 13. <hi>They fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the wordes of the Prophets, the which are read euery Sabboth.</hi> And chap. 15. <hi>For Moſes of olde hath them in euerie Citie,
<pb facs="tcp:3777:22"/> which preach him, when as hee is read in the Sinagogues euerie Sabboth.</hi> And cap. 17. <hi>And Paule, as his cuſtome was, went in vnto them, and three Sabboth daies diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them, out of the ſcripture, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">proues for priuate in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction &amp; admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition.</note> As touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of miniſters in priuate inſtruction and admonition, we read. Act. 17. <hi>He reaſoned in the Sinagogue with the Iewes, and religious perſons, &amp; in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket daily with all that he met.</hi> And cap. 20. <hi>Take heed therefore vnto your ſelues, and vnto the whole flocke in the which the holye Ghoſt hath made you ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers to feede the church of God, &amp;c.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: <hi>Watch therfore, remembring, that I, by the ſpace of three yeares ceaſed not day and night with teares to admoniſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one.</hi> 2. Tim. 4. <hi>Preach the word, bee earneſt in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon: rebuke, reprooue, exhort with all mildeneſſe and doctrine. But watch thou in all thinges, ſuffer, do the worke of an Euangeliſt,<note place="margin">2 To mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>craments.</note> giue full proofe of thy miniſterie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To miniſter the Sacramentes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the ordinance of God. And as doctrine, ſo alſo the adminiſtration of the Sacraments is not tied vnto thoſe daies, in which the méetings of the Church are
<pb facs="tcp:3777:23"/> made, but it is ſufficient concerning the publike miniſtration, if it be done by the miniſters of the church, as thoſe which do repreſent a publike perſon, and roome of God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſterie ſpeaking vnto men, and that thoſe things be done in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyes of the Church, the which God hath tied vnto the miniſters. So circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was miniſtred at anye daye which was the eight day after the birth of the childe: ſo baptiſme may be miniſtred on any day. Act 8. &amp;. 10. Yet the miniſtring of the Sacrament ought eſpecially to bee vſed on the Sabboth daye. And therefore Numb 28. and. 29. beſides the daily ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, there are alſo ſet forth certaine ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices which ought to be vſed on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, and other holy dayes And Chriſt in ſuch ſort ordained his ſupper, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which among other endes, ought alſo to be the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowe of the Congregation of the church, that it might be miniſtred either in a ſmall or great aſſembly of the Church.</p>
               <p>Matth. 26. <hi>Drinke ye all of this.</hi> 1. Cor. 10. <hi>The bread which wee breake, is it not the communion of the bodie of Chriſt? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we being manie are one bread, one
<pb facs="tcp:3777:23"/> bodie. For all wee are partakers of one bread.</hi> And chap. 11. <hi>Therefore when yee come together into one place, this is not to eate the Lords ſupper. For euery one eateth his own ſupper before.</hi> In the ſame place, <hi>Therfore (my brethere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) when ye come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to eate, tarrie one for another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And vnto the lawfull adminiſtration of the Sacraments appertaineth alſo the ſhutting out of thoſe,<note place="margin">Shutting out of the vnvvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie.</note> whome God hath commanded to be ſhut out from them.</p>
               <p>Like as it was not lawfull for ſtrangers from the nation and religion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, nor for the vncircumciſed to eate the Paſchall Lambe. Exod. 12. ſo the Church of God ought not to admit or receiue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Supper of the Lorde, ſuch as are not baptized, or ſuch as being baptized, yet in doctrine or manners are ſtrangers from Chriſtianitie.</p>
               <p>To learne the doctrine of the Church,<note place="margin">3 To learn the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church.</note> that is, to come often vnto the aſſemblies of the Church, to heare and learne the heauenly doctrine, and diligentlye to meditate and examine the doctrine being heard, and eſpeciallye to beſtowe the dayes appoynted for the miniſterie, in
<pb facs="tcp:3777:24"/> reading, ſtudying, and handling of diuine matters: for inaſmuch as God will haue miniſters of the Church to be, he will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that there bée hearers of the doctrine, and the ſame alſo diligent. And the deſire to learne is not without priuate medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therfore they of <hi>Bercea</hi> are praiſed, Acts. 17. for that they receiued the worde with all ioyfulneſſe, dailie ſearching the Scriptures, whether the thinges were ſo or no: and eſpeciall to ſuch as ſerue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, or meane in time to come to ſerue the Church a diligent ſtudie to know the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is inioyned. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Take heede vnto reading, exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doctrine: foreſlow not the gifte which is in thee, the which was giuen th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to propheſie, with the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of the hands of the olderſhip. Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe theſe things: in theſe be thou, that thy profiting m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y be manifeſt vnto all. Take heed vnto thy ſelfe, and vnto doctrine: in theſe continue. For if thou doe this, thou ſhalt ſaue thy ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lfe, and thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eare thee.</hi> And 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ule</hi> will haue a min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter of the Church to bee fit to teach, and to confute and ouerthrow t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> aduerſaries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>To vſe the Sacraments according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:3777:24"/> the ordinance of God.<note place="margin">To vſe the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</note> So God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Paſſeouer to be kept in the aſſembly of the people, and appoynted certaine ſacrifices vnto other feaſt dayes and Sabboths. Alſo Act. 20. <hi>The firſt day of the weeke, when as the Diſciples were come together to breake bread, Paul prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, &amp;c.</hi> For as God will haue true doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine to be heard, ſo he will alſo haue the lawfull vſe of the ſacraments to be ſéene in the publike aſſemblyes of the Church: becauſe that he will haue both theſe to be a note, whereby the Church may be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen and diſcerned from other nations &amp; ſectes. The ſacraments alſo, like as the word, are an inſtrument, or exerciſe to ſtirre vp and maintaine faith and godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in vs. They are alſo a publike pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our faith and thankfulneſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and a part of the publike worſhip of God in the church. And therfore the vſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is moſt eſpecialy agreeable vnto the Sabboth.</p>
               <p>Publike calling vpon God, wherby we do ioyne our confeſſion, thanks-giuing,<note place="margin">5 Publike calling on God.</note> and prayers with the church. For God wil be called vpon not onely priuately of euerye man, but alſo publikely by the
<pb facs="tcp:3777:25"/> Church, for his glorie, and our comfort, to wit, that we ſhould not doubt, that we are heard of God, when as he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed hearing not onely vnto vs, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnto others, and vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole church, praying for vs together with vs. For to this ende he hath added a peculiar pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vnto common praiers, Matth. 18. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I ſay vnto you, if two of you ſhal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together vpon earth, whatſoeuer they ſhall aske, it ſhall be graunted vnto them of my father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the middeſt of them.</hi> And thankes-giuing and the prayſing of God, is promiſed vnto God as an eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all worſhip. Pſal. 22. <hi>In the middeſt of the Congregation I will praiſe thee. Of thee ſhall bee my praiſe in a Congregation of much people, I will pay my vowes before them that feare him.</hi> And it is commanded 1. Cor 14. <hi>Foraſmuch as if thou bleſſe in ſpirit, he which occupieth the roome of an vnlearned perſon, how ſhall he ſay Amen vnto thy thankes-giuing? For he knoweth not what thou ſaieſt.</hi> And. 1. Tim. 2. <hi>I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort therefore before all things, that there be made ſupplications, prayers, requeſts, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3777:25"/> thankes-giuing, for all men, for Kings, and for al that are ſet in authoritie, that we may lead a quiet &amp; a peaceable life in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and chaſtitie, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither doth Chriſt in the 6. of Matth. condemne and forbid publike prayers,<note place="margin">Matth. 6. Not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pocriſie is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</note> but boaſting &amp; hypocriſie, ſaying: <hi>When thou prayeſt, enter into thy chamber, and ſhutting thy doore pray vnto thy Father which is in ſecret, and thy father which ſeeth thee in ſecret, ſhal reward thee open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> The wordes going before do witneſſe this: <hi>When thou prayeſt, be not as the hypocrites. For they loue to pray ſtanding in their aſſemblies and corners of the ſtreetes, that they maye be ſeene of men. Verely I ſay vnto you, they haue their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> And hypocriſie is a counterfaiting &amp; boaſting and vaine ſhewing of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Taring therefore this,<note place="margin">Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</note> he ſpeaketh not of the deſire to pleaſe god, and of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him as well publikely as priuately, but he will haue thoſe alſo which praye publikely, to haue regarde not vnto the iudgement and eyes of men but of God concerning vs, and not to looke vnto our glorie, but vnto the glorie of God.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3777:26"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">6 The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teining</note>
                  <hi>The honour of the miniſterie of the Church,</hi> which containeth many things: firſt, reuerence, that is an acknowledging of the order and wil of God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and preſeruation of the miniſterie, and the gathering together of the church by the ſame,<note place="margin">1 Reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> and the declaration &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of this our iudgement of the miniſterie both in wordes and déedes.</p>
               <p>1. Cor. 4. <hi>Let a man ſo eſteeme of vs as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and diſpoſers of the ſecrets of God.</hi> 2. Cor. 5. <hi>Therefore we are Embaſſadours in the name of Chriſt, as if God intre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ted you by vs: wee praye you in the name of Chriſt, that ye be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vnto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Loue.</note>Secondly, Loue, by the which we wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly both reſort vnto the aſſemblies of the church, and do heare and learne the doctrine of the church, and do wiſh well vnto the faithful miniſters of the church, not onely in reſpect of the dutie of loue, but alſo in regard of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſterie which they execute. Pſal. 84. <hi>How amiable are thy Tabernacles O Lord of hoſtes. My ſoule longeth, yea, and fainteth for the Courtes of the Lord, my heart &amp; my fleſh reioyce in the liuing God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3777:26"/>
               <p>Pſal. 122. <hi>I reioyced with them that ſayd vnto me, we will goe into the houſe of the Lord.</hi> Alſo, <hi>For my bretheren ſake I will now ſpeake peace of thee, becauſe of the houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek thy good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, obedience in thoſe thinges,<note place="margin">3 Obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> which appertaine vnto the miniſterie. Hebr. 4. <hi>Obey your Rulers.</hi> Hethertoo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine the workes of loue towardes God, and towards our neighbor, that is, the whole life of a Chriſtian, which is the ſpirituall Sabboth For it is nothing els to kéepe a ſpirituall Sabboth,<note place="margin">To keepe a ſpiritual Sabboth.</note> then in the ordering of our life to obey the voyce of God ſounding by the miniſterie of the Church. For God will haue the doctrine learned to this ende, that it may be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Iam. 1. <hi>Performe ye the word in deed, and be not hearers onely, deceiuing your ſelues: becauſe if a man be a hearer of the word and not a doer, he ſhall be compared vnto a man beholding the countenance of his birth in a glaſſe, for hee hath behelde himſelfe, and went his waye, and by and by forgetteth what manner one he was.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, for as much as he will haue this
<pb facs="tcp:3777:27"/> Sabboth to be kepte all our life time, hée will haue the examples and teſtimonies of the ſame eſpecially to be ſhewed forth on the outward or ceremoniall Sabboth day, that is, at thoſe times which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for the teaching and learning of the word of God.<note place="margin">He that hath no care to ſerue the Lord on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day, vvill not ſerue him at other times.</note> For if a man al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time doo not ſhewe foorth a deſire to obey God, when as the doctrine ringeth in his eares, and when as other cares being laid aſide, God will haue vs to thinke vpon godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and repentance, he ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth that he will not doo it at another time.</p>
               <p>There it hath alwayes bene the manner in the Church, on the Sabboth day to giue almes, &amp; to exerciſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of loue towardes the néedie. Nehem. 8. <hi>Send parts vnto him for whom nothing is prepared, becauſe it is an holy daye vnto our Lord.</hi> God himſelfe alſo doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Deut. 5. that he will haue the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both kept, that reſt maye be giuen to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts and to our familie: leaſt that with the continuaunce of laboures they ſhould be too much brought downe. And 1. Corinth 16. <hi>Furthermore as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:3777:27"/> the gathering for the Saintes, as I haue appoynted vnto the Churches of Galatia, ſo doo yee alſo. Euerie firſt daye of the weeke, let euerie one of you laye a ſide with himſelfe, laying vp that, which thorough the gentleneſſe of GOD he maye.</hi> And Actes 2. all theſe works of the Sabboth are ioyntly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed together: <hi>The Diſciples were abiding in the doctrine of the Apoſtles, and in fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhippe, and breaking of bread, and prayers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthlye,<note place="margin">4 Thankful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> honour comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alſo Thankfulneſſe, that is, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties concerning the preſeruation of the Miniſterie and Miniſters. For if GOD will haue a Miniſterie to be in the Church, hée will alſo that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye one, according to their abilitie, doo further the maintenaunce of the ſame, that is, that they beſtowe theyr money and trauayle vpon the nouriſhing and defending of godly Miniſters and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</p>
               <p>Hethertoo appertaine the lawes of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, concerning the firſt borne, firſt fruits, tenthes, and very many offerings, the
<pb facs="tcp:3777:28"/> which were appointed vnto the Prieſtes &amp; Leuites in ſteade of a ſtipend, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to maintaine the life of them and theirs, that they might attend vppon the miniſterie. Albeit the circumſtaunces of theſe lawes be aboliſhed &amp; taken awaie, yet the generall remaineth for euer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God will haue the miniſterie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued euen vntill the end of the worlde. <hi>Deu.</hi> 12. <hi>Take heed vnto thy ſelfe that thou forſake not the Leuite all thy daies vppon thy land.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>Who goeth on warfare at anie time vpon his owne charges? Who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof? Or who feedeth a flocke, and eateth not of the milke of the flocke? Doth not the lawe alſo ſaie theſe things? For it is written in the lawe of Moſes, Thou ſhalt not muſle the mouth of the Oxe, that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out the corne.</hi> Alſo, <hi>If we haue ſowen vnto you ſpirituall things, is it a great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if we reap your fleſhlie things?</hi> Again, <hi>Are ye ignorant, that they which ſerue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout holie thinges, doe eate of the thinges which are of the altar? And they that ſerue at the altar, doe take parte of the altar? So the Lord hath ordeined, that they which preach the Goſpell, ſhould liue of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3777:28"/> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. <hi>The elders which doe rule well, let them be counted worthie of dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble honour, eſpeciallie thoſe that do labour in the word and in doctrine. For the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, Thou ſhalt not muſle vp the mouth of the Oxe, that treadeth out the corne. And the worke-man is worthie of his hire. Math.</hi> 10. <hi>He that receiueth a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the name of a Prophet, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the reward of a Prophet.</hi> Héerevnto alſo pertaineth the examples of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> nouriſhing the Prophet <hi>Elias.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 17. Of <hi>Obadiah</hi> ſauing the Prophets, whome <hi>Iezabel</hi> did perſecute. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 18. Of the Church of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> letting downe <hi>Paule</hi> by the wall Acts. 9.</p>
               <p>In this part of the honour towardes the miniſterie is alſo conteined the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of ſchooles:<note place="margin">Schooles.</note> inaſmuch as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſtudies of learning and arts men are neither fit to teach, neither can the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of doctrine be preſerued and defended againſt Heretikes. Therefore Chriſt Math. 11. promiſeth a reward vnto thoſe, the which for the furtherance and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of doctrine do well vnto thoſe which doe either alreadie teach, or which are in time to come to teach, or whoſe trauaile
<pb facs="tcp:3777:29"/> doth ſerue, or ſhall héereafter ſerue for the preſeruation of doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5 Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of miniſters</note>Fiftlie and laſtlie, vnto this honour of the miniſterie is alſo required vprightnes or gentleneſſe in bearing with the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the miniſters, the which doe not notoriouſlie or manifeſtlie corrupt or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlow their office, &amp; hurt the Church with offence. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. <hi>Receiue not an accuſation againſt an Elder, but vnder two or three witneſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traries &amp; repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vvorkes of the Sabboth.</note>Foraſmuch then as this is the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or hallowing of the Sabboth, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that the thinges wherewith the Sabboth is prophaned or broken, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vnto theſe workes.</p>
               <p>Againſt the teaching of doctrine is ſet the leauing or forſlowing of the duetie of teaching,<note place="margin">1 Vnto do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> either priuatelie or publiklie. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. <hi>All her watch-men are dumbe dogges, which are not able to barke, ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, taking their eaſe, verie diligent to ſleepe. And they are rauenous dogges, which knowe not when they are full, and the Shepheardes themſelues vnderſtande nothing, they haue all gone aſide after their owne waie, euerie one vnto his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe in his place. Ezech.</hi> 34. <hi>Woe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:3777:29"/> the Shepheardes that haue fedde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: Doe not ſhepheardes feede their flocke? Yee haue eaten the fat, and doo cloath your ſelues with the wooll: ye haue killed the fat, but haue not fed the ſheepe: the weake haue ye not comforted, and the ſicke haue yee not healed, and the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken haue ye not bound vp, that that was caſt downe yee haue not brought againe, &amp; that which was loſt ye haue not ſought, but ye haue reigned ouer them cruellie and tyrannouſlie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo corrupting and mangling of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or bowing of the ſame vnto the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> opinions, affections, deſires, or profite of the miniſters, or magiſtrates, or others. 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2. <hi>For wee doe not, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, make merchaundiſe of the woorde of GOD, but wee ſpeake of Chriſt, as of ſinceritie, as of GOD, in the ſight of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt the adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes is either the leauing or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlowing of the exhortation of the Church to vſe the Sacramentes,<note place="margin">2 Vnto the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</note> or an vnlawfull admiſtration, when as ſome thing is either taken from the ceremonies ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3777:30"/> by God, or when ſome thing is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in them, or when as ſuch are ſhut out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sacraments, as ought to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or ſuch receiued which by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God ought to be kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, or when as the people are not inſtructed concerning the right vſe of them.<note place="margin">3 Againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſire to learne doctrine.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt the deſire to learne doctrine, is the contempt &amp; neglecting of doctrine, that is, either not to be preſent at holie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, when there is no lawfull cauſe to let vs, and on the Sabboth to doe workes that might be put off vntill another time, or to giue no eares vnto holie Sermons, or not to meditate and ſearch the doctrine of the Church, but eſpeciallie negligence to knowe the doctrine in the miniſters, or in thoſe, which by God are called vnto the ſtudie of doctrine, and either ought one daie to ſerue vnto the ſetting forth of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, or haue greater occaſion and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to learne the ſame, then others. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.<note place="margin">He that gathereth ſtickes. Death ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointed for the Sabboth breakers.</note> He that gathered ſticks on the Sabboth daie, is ſtoned to death. And <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> 31. Paine of death is ſet down againſt them that on the Sabboth doe works hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the miniſterie. <hi>Nehem,</hi> 13. They that doe ſuch workes on the Sabboth are
<pb facs="tcp:3777:30"/> verie ſharplie chidden. <hi>Math.</hi> 13. As often as a man heareth the word of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and vnderſtandeth it not, then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that wicked one, and taketh awaie that which was ſowen in his heart. This is he which receiueth the ſéede by the way ſide, &amp;c. <hi>Math.</hi> 15. <hi>Let them alone, they are blinde, guides of the blinde: if the blinde leade the blinde, they both fall into the ditch. Luke</hi> 12. <hi>Vnto whome ſo euer much hath bene giuen, much ſhall be required of him againe, and with whom they haue laid downe much, the more they will aske a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at his hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo curioſitie, the which is a deſire to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> know or to heare things not reuealed by God, not neceſſarie, or new things <hi>Pro.</hi> 25 <hi>As to eate much honie, is not good: ſo the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rching out of the glorie of the diuine things is no glorie.</hi> Sonne of Sirach. 3. <hi> Search not vnconſideratlie after thinges that are more hard then thou art able to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto: and concerning things that are aboue thy power, fooliſhlie ſeeke not after them. The thinges that are commaunded thee of God, the ſame ſtudie thou holilie vpon. For it is not needfull for thee, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde with thine eyes the thinges that are
<pb facs="tcp:3777:31"/> ſecret: the things that are not neceſſarie, but ſuperfluous vnto thy talke, meddle not curiouſlie with them. For mo thinges are opened vnto thee, then the wit of man is able to comprehend.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Giue no eare vnto fables, and endleſſe genealogies, the which doe rather breed queſtions, then edifying of God, which is by faith.</hi> And Chapter 4. <hi>Prophane and olde wiues fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles reiect.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>Reiect or caſt awaie fooliſh and vnlearned queſtions, knowing that they doe breede ſtrifes. Tit.</hi> 3. <hi>Refrain fooliſh queſtions and genealogies, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and ſtrifes about the lawe: for they are vnprofitable and vaine.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>There will be a time when as they ſhal not abide ſound doctrine, but itching in their eares, they according vnto their owne luſtes, ſhall heape vp vnto themſelues teachers, and ſhall turne awaie their eares from the truth, and bee turned vnto fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Vnto the lawfull vſe and receiuing of the Sacraments is repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the leauing off and contempt of the ſame. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning of them, when as they are vſed and receiued, not after that ſorte which
<pb facs="tcp:3777:31"/> God hath commaunded, or not of thoſe, for whome they were ordained. Alſo ſuperſtitious receiuing, when as ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the grace of GOD are tied vnto the obſeruation of the ceremonies, or elſe are vſed vnto other endes wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they are not ordained by GOD. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Hee that is vncircumciſed ſhall be rooted out from among his people. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> 4. GOD threatneth death vnto Moſes becauſe of his ſonne which was not circumciſed. <hi>Malach.</hi> 1. <hi>The Lord of hoaſts ſayth vnto you. O Prieſts, which contemne my name, and haue ſayd, Wherein haue wee contemned thy name? Which doe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vppon mine altar, polluted bread, and yee haue ſayd, wherein haue wee polluted the ſame? &amp;c. Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi> 66. <hi>Hee that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth an Oxe, dooth ſinne as much as hee that ſlayeth a man, &amp;c.</hi> 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11. <hi>Hee that eateth and drinketh vnworthilie, eateth and drinketh vnto himſelfe damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vnto the publike praiers,<note place="margin">5 Vnto pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting of them, and the hypocriticall béeing preſent at them without eare-giuing
<pb facs="tcp:3777:32"/> or affection. Alſo the rehearſing of them not ſeruing vnto the edifying of the Church. 1. Cor. 14. <hi>If thou bleſſe in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, he, which occupieth the roome of an ignorant perſon, how ſhall hee ſay Amen vnto thy giuing of thankes? For he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not what thou ſaiſt. For thou giueſt thankes well, but another is not edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In like manner alſo is againſt the vſe and exerciſe of the whole miniſterie, not onely the particular leauing of duetie in euerie priuate perſon, but by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or any manner of hinderance, by his commaundement or perſwaſion, the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away of his children, familie, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, from the vſe and exerciſe of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">6 Vnto the honor of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie.</note>Vnto the honour of the Miniſterie, the contempt and deſpiſing of the ſame is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, whereby either the miniſterie of of the Church is aboliſhed and taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, or is committed vnto vnworthye perſons, or is denied to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtrument y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which God will vſe for the gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of his Church: or when as the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are reproched. 1. Tim. 5. <hi>Laye not thy handes quickly vnto any man, neither
<pb facs="tcp:3777:32"/> be thou partaker of other mens ſinnes.</hi> Luke. 10. <hi>Hee that deſpiſeth you, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth mee.</hi> Or when as they are hated, Matth. 10. and 24. <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all men for my names ſake.</hi> Or when as doctrine is not obeyed in the leading of our life: but eſpecially when as on the Sabboth daye, the workes of loue &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe are neglected, and the time im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed vnto vaine and wicked things, or ſpent in lewdneſſe: or when as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie maintenance is not giuen vnto the Miniſters, defence and other dueties of thankefulneſſe and courteſie are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed vnto them: that I ſaye nothing, when as the Miniſters are wronged and hurte: when as the maintenance of ſchooles and learning is not cared for: or els when as the infirmities and wants in the miniſters that may be borne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, are bitterly taunted, or when as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of them the miniſterie is deſpiſed or neglected.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>To God be all praiſe and glorie.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3777:33"/>Ierem. 17. ver. 21.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>THus ſaith the Lord: Take heede vnto your ſelues: and carrie no burthens on the Sabboth day, or bring them in into the gates of Ieruſalem.</p>
                  <p n="22">22 Neither carrie out burthens out of your houſes on the Sabboth daie, nor do ye anie worke: but ſanctifie and keepe holie the Sabboth daie, as I commanded your el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
                  <p n="23">23 Who hearkned not, nor bowed their eare: but hardned their necke, not hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nor receiuing inſtruction.</p>
                  <p n="24">24 For it ſhall come to paſſe, that if by obeying ye will obey me, the ſaying of the Lord, in not bringing in burthens into the gates of the Citie on the Sabboth day: and in ſanctifying and hallowing of the Sabboth daie, that ye doe no work therin.</p>
                  <p n="25">
                     <note place="margin">A bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sabboth.</note>25 That kings and Princes ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the gates of this Citie, ſitting vpon the throne of Dauid, and riding on chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots and horſes, they and their Princes, and the men of Iuda, and the inhabitants of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and this citie ſhall remaine for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
                  <p n="26">
                     <pb facs="tcp:3777:33"/>26 And they ſhall come out of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Iuda, and from places about Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and alſo out of the land of Beniamin, both out of a low place, &amp; out of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and from the South part, bringing burnt offerings and ſacrifice, and gifts with franckinſence, and bringing offeringes of thanks-giuing vnto the houſe of the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="27">27 But if ye will not obey me,<note place="margin">A puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment for the break<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers of the Sabboth.</note> to ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Sabboth daie, and not carrye bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens entering into the gates of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the Sabboth daie: certainlie I will kindle a fire in the gates thereof, which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the pallaces of Ieruſalem, and ſhal not be quenched.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
